All right, okay, is this projecting at all?
Can everyone hear me?
Give me the back.
We get, awesome.
All right, so welcome everyone to the first lecture
of CS61A.
Yeah!
APPLAUSE
Wow, I'm so glad that got a response.
So this is, I'm super glad to see this lecture in so full.
So let's just go ahead and jump in to the first lecture.
Before we talk about anything relating to computer science,
first we're going to talk about 6.1A as a class,
starting with the 6.1A community.
So first of all, hi, my name's Chris.
I'm going to be one of your instructors.
My pronouns are they, them.
And I've been teaching 6.1A for a while.
I've been a TA for five semesters involved a bit before that.
And this is my first time as an instructor for this course.
So I'm really excited.
Some might interest within computer science
our computational biology and programming languages.
So if you want to talk about that or really anything
in the course, you can feel free to reach out.
I'm going to go ahead and pass around this mic.
There's going to be a little bit of like,
some noise is going on.
Let's see.
Yeah.
My name's Debbie.
This is, I'll be one of your other lecturers in the summer.
This is my eight time teaching the course.
So my first time lecture, in terms of computer science,
my interest in computer security
and a demo some research in agritorial and out.
So if you find yourself interested in that later
on the course, which we'll try to talk to me,
also this is a really difficult course.
So we're all here to talk to you about anything
if you've ever needed.
So free email on us, I think that's it.
I'll be one of the other three instructors.
My research interests are kind of probably
language design, as well as the applications
to CS education in particular.
This is also taught it for a fair amount.
Excited to be.
Cool.
All right, so I'll take this back.
So if you ever want to contact us,
you should email us at CS61A plus SU19 at Berkeley.edu.
If you email us there, you'll be able to,
all three of us will see that.
So that's the best way to contact us.
You can also reach out to us individually
if you have something pertaining to one of us
as individuals, but this is the email you should be
looking at for the most part.
So we're here in Struck.
We're also here coming in.
There's a lot of seats on this side.
So it's so pretty to go in on the other entry.
And those are like seats in experts.
So maybe if you're in the middle area,
we could like switch together a little bit,
really just coming in.
Yeah, there's a seat next to you,
and you can move to the center.
Let's do that so people coming in can do that.
Awesome.
I'll give like a minute for the noise to settle here.
All right, so you've met us.
We're going to be your instructors,
but there's just three of us,
and there's like 400 plus a view in this room.
So there's no way we can do all this by ourselves,
which is why we have a wonderful team of TAs,
as well as tutors.
So TAs are responsible for running lab and discussion sections.
You'll see them in office hours.
Tutors are responsible for running smaller group tutoring
sections, which we'll talk about a little bit later.
But both TAs and tutors are going to be the people you're
going to be interacting with most often throughout the course.
So with that in mind, we have a bunch of them
up here on stage, so I'm going to go ahead
and try to pass down the mic when you get it.
If you can just give your name, your role.
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, if you can come down here
and pass it down, yeah.
So I have like two cables tethering me down.
It's a lot of fun.
OK, I want to make TAs an Albert.
I want to be part of the new grading,
so I'll give you why as TAs, and then I'll also be doing
a little bit of the T, that music's on the side,
so maybe this is not a whole domain of TAs,
but I've got to give you some money on my music,
so it's an opportunity to talk about that,
to give you the objective.
Hello, I'm Richard.
I took six to make last summer.
I'm going to be a TAs this summer.
I'm really excited to be teaching about it, so.
And while I'm running on one of the other materials,
and I do content for the projects.
Hello, my name is Jason.
I'm going to be TAs this summer,
and you can feel free to come here in one second.
Hi, I'm Olivia, I'm a TAs, and I think
we're just a little bit more in.
I'm also TAs, and I'm going to be working
on the online content itself.
Welcome.
Hi, I'm Edo, and I'm a TAs.
Hi, I'm Michelle, and welcome with Olivia,
and I'm a little bit of just six.
Hi, I'm Edo, and I'm TAs, and I'm TAs, and I'm TAs.
Hi, I'm Jenny, first, and I'm from the classical century.
Woo!
Thank you.
All right, y'all can feel free to add back a little bit.
All right, okay, so again, these tutors and TAs
are going to be the people you're going to be
interacting with the most throughout the semester.
So once you start going to lab and discussion,
these are the people that you should be sure to get to know,
and they'll be the best people to handle
most of your questions and concerns in this course.
In addition to TAs and tutors, we also have a very, very
large group of academic interns.
Academic interns are students who usually recently
took the class, and they'll be helping out in your lab
and office hour sections to give you some help with the assignments.
This is like a very small subset of the people we'll have
helping out as AI's over the summer, so you'll
be seeing a lot of those as well.
And then, in addition to TAs, tutors, instructors,
and academic interns, we have the most important people
in this course, all of you.
Yeah.
APPLAUSE
Very much not used to all this applause, but I don't know.
Yeah, it comes with a job, I guess.
So yeah, over the summer, this is by far the largest group
of students we've ever had for summer course,
across the in-person 61A and online 6.1A sections.
We have over 650 people enrolled in this course.
And all of us are really, really excited
to be able to work with all of you and put on a great class
semester.
Really excited to be able to talk to you and work
with you through all of this.
So with that, let's start talking about 6.1A in particular.
So 6.1A is a class in the computer science department.
For many of you, it might be your first computer science class.
So what is computer science?
Computer science is a very broad field.
But in general, computer science is the study
of different problems that can be solved using computation.
So all computation means is that you do some series of steps.
Maybe you're doing some math or just following some instructions
to be able to get some result.
This doesn't even need to be done with computers.
In fact, in the early days, if you just
had someone write a bunch of math,
you might even call them computers.
But more specifically, computer science
is how do you take these problems and solve the different approaches
for being able to solve these problems?
So there are a bunch of different ways
you can approach different problems.
A bunch of different ways you can solve them with computation.
And computer science talks about some
of those different approaches.
In particular, we are interested in the techniques
that lead to the most effective solutions.
So of course, some solutions will take more time or require
more resources than others.
So we're interested in the solutions
that are going to be the most effective.
One other thing to note is that not all problems
can be solved effectively through computation.
For example, a lot of problems out there
will require you to actually, I don't know, interact with people.
And those tasks aren't very easily solved
by just a list of steps you can blindly follow.
So it's important to note that computer science
doesn't tell you how to solve every problem.
But there's a great variety of problems
that it can solve.
And we're interested in effective solutions
for those problems.
So what are some of these different problems that you can solve?
So there's systems like operating systems,
compilers, artificial intelligence, graphics,
so on and so forth.
There's a big long list.
These are just a subset of the interests
that people at Berkeley have as their research interests.
But just about any of these topics,
if you're interested in, you can ultimately
take a class in at Berkeley or elsewhere.
By the way, if you're sitting in the back,
we still do have quite a few seats on this side of the room
if you want to move over and not clog up the rows.
So, are these ways probably exiting
and then going through the other entry?
There's another door on this side,
so if you exit the ground.
Of course.
So that's computer science.
What is 61A in particular about?
Well, it's about managing complexity.
So a lot of these problems can have really
complicated and large solutions.
And one important skill to be able to have
is how to take these solutions and express them
in a really simple and effective way.
One of the ways we teach this in this course
is through mastering abstraction.
So what abstraction means is for most things you run across,
you don't need to know exactly how they work.
You can take some of the complicated details
and, well, abstract them away.
So for example, when you're interacting with other people,
when you see human being, you don't see them
as a collection of cells or a bunch of chemical processes
happening, you interact with them as humans.
So you abstract away all those chemical and biological
processes and view them as a human.
With programs, instead of looking at the very minute details
of what's going on, we'll see different ways
to group them and abstract them.
One of those ways is by exposing you to different programming
paradigms.
So programming paradigms are just different ways
to approach writing programs.
And a lot of these have very general abstract differences.
So across this course, we'll be exposing you
to imperative, declarative, functional,
several different types of programming.
And these are different ways that you can organize your program
and help manage its complexity.
Of course, 61A, again, is many of your first computer science
classes, so we also hope for it to serve
as an introduction to program.
So we'll hope that we can give you
a pretty full understanding of Python fundamentals.
After you go through this course, you
should be able to do a lot in Python.
We also take a lot of smaller ideas
that will teach in lecture and discussion in lab
and combine those into larger projects, which
is an important skill to be able to have
when you're in the real world, because most of what you're
going to be doing is large projects.
And finally, we'll talk a little bit
about how computers interpret programming languages.
So when you write code, how does your computer actually
take that code and how is it able to run it?
In the beginning of the course, we'll
talk about this more mechanically.
So we'll have you actually do some of the interpretation
yourself.
But later in the course, we'll talk about how computers
can interpret programming languages automatically.
And finally, this is a challenging course
that will demand a lot for me.
The pace of this course is very fast.
There's going to be a lot of assignments.
However, if you do choose to stick with this class,
we have a lot of resources available,
and we do really want you to succeed.
So please don't understand the pace and difficulty
of this class, but also understand
that there's a lot of things available for you
if you want to stick with this class.
That being said, this class isn't the right first programming
or computer science class for everyone.
And with that in mind, there are a couple of alternatives
to CS61A that you might want to keep in mind.
So the first one is CS10, called the beauty and joy
of computing.
CS10 is designed for students who do not have prior experience.
So even though in 61A, we try to make the course such
that you can still succeed.
Even if you don't have prior programming experience,
I didn't have prior programming experience
when I took the course, for example.
However, CS10 is specifically designed
for students without prior experience.
So for some students, this is a better fit for your first class.
This is an introduction to some of the fundamentals
of computer science.
It does go over some Python, although some of the class
is also in a language called snap, which
is more of a visual language.
But after going through CS10, you'll
know a lot of the concepts and Python fundamentals
that you'll need for 61A.
Right now, it has a shortest waitlist.
And over the summer, it has been taught by Matthew and Monty.
So you can see more info at cs10.org.
There's also data eight, which is the foundations of data science.
So data goes over the fundamentals of computing
of statistical inference and some a little bit
of machine learning applied to real world data sets.
So the purpose of data eight is a little bit different
than CS61A.
CS61A is a class about computer science.
Data eight is a class about data science,
which is a little bit different because it's more concerned
with how you process data, but there is still
quite a bit of overlap.
It does feature more statistics than computer science.
However, the programming isn't 61A,
so it is a good exposure to Python if you want to take that
before 61A.
If you want to enroll, it's listed as CSC8,
although it's referred to as data eight.
It has a little bit of a larger waitlist,
but it is being taught over the summer by Natalia and Francie.
It's actually the lecture right before this one.
So you'll probably run to them as they're exiting the hall.
All right.
So more info on data eight.org.
So I'm going to go ahead and hand it off to Tiffany
to talk a little bit about the course logistics,
again, pardon me, as there's a little bit of noise here.
So we're trying to get screencasts for most of these lectures,
which means we need both the mic to project
and another mic to record.
So it's a little bit of technical setup.
We'll talk a bit about that in a minute.
So I'm going to talk a bit about course format
and concretely just, so first off,
this course has a lot of different components.
I'll just do the thing right now.
There's a lecture that'll be every Monday
through Thursday at 11 a.m. in this room.
Lecture is where you're going to be exposed
to course material for the first time.
So we strongly encourage you to come in person.
So you see the lecture before your discussion,
because generally, although your change
is very kind, it will be we need discussions most effective
if you've seen the relevant lecture beforehand.
There's also a lab, discussion and office analysis.
The reason that these are all labeled
the most important part of the course
is because it really depends on the student
and we encourage you to both.
You should really complete all of them,
and you'll see that probably one of them
will be the most effective for your learning.
The lab is the place where you'll usually,
after lecture before discussion,
you're going to actually interact with your machine
to do some programming in the soda labs.
This is where you'll get to interact with a lot of concepts
for the first time in discussion.
You're going to actually be working on pen and paper.
And you may be wondering, why do we do that?
This is because this course is actually quite theoretical.
This isn't a programming course.
You will learn programming over the course of the course,
but that was not meant to be like a hot rhyme.
That isn't the focus.
The focus is giving you a foundation and computer science.
And that's why discussion where you go over questions
with a pen and paper is a really fundamental part of the course
and happens after a lab once you've got your fundamentals down.
All this hours are where you can drop by to ask any questions.
Oftentimes, we'll come with a side of questions
because the assignments are very challenging.
This is where you'll interact with a lot of the active
in the interns as well.
And then, we also have an online textbook.
Some students read this textbook,
and the chapter is associated.
You'll feed on the website.
Every lecture has associated text and chapters.
Some students read this before lecture.
Some students read this after lecture.
Some students don't read this textbook at all.
I don't know about the key here, how much of the text works.
But we highly encourage you for a use of first
D to read the text book and see what you're
trying to help for.
Personally, a lot of the text books.
And I think, because now it's going to read the text book,
because it's not a color.
I'm not trying to say both are normal and acceptable.
But ultimately, it just depends on what your learning style is.
So try it out and see what works for you.
And there's also weekly homework assignments
for big program projects, a midterm and a final.
And the reason we're listing all this
is to say, it will be very demanding.
And this is what you can expect.
But there also will be a lot of support along the way.
Any questions?
Yeah, in the front.
So the program is going to be able to program the project
all the time.
Yes.
Holly, you put it in the program you project.
You wouldn't believe the point is.
But you're like, yeah, so there are four projects.
There are a lot of means about them online.
And soon, you'll be able to relate to those movies.
So in terms of the first week, you just logistics.
Lab will start in Wednesday.
So even if you have a Monday or Tuesday
lab not happening this week, because that's just set up.
Do the lab on your own.
Stop it all.
The stars if you need help, but set up.
Just one quick announcement about Lab Zero.
On Piazza, some of you were mentioning
that you were running into some issues with Lab Zero.
I think we found that some students running in Map OS
are able to run Lab Zero.
So we're working on fixing that.
So this is not working for you.
We'll let you know when you can read download it,
and it should be fixed.
This is an example of debugging on the spot.
There'll be a left-shandered bug you see.
But yeah, we'll have a fix up shortly,
and you should keep an eye on Piazza.
In terms of discussion, discussions start on Tuesday.
And we highly encourage you to attend the discussion
of matches your lab.
You can see on the base in your discussion number,
you can see whether they've mapped your lab.
They should have the same pattern.
The reason for this is so that you see the same Pia,
and they get to know you, and they'll
be able to help you much more effectively.
It's also better organizationally for hours.
And finally, office hours will also start on Tuesday.
There are no office hours today.
OK, so in terms of attendance,
we do not select luxury tenants at all.
But as I said, you highly encourage you to attend.
This is our first time trying to webcast the summer session.
So we'll try to make it as involved as you can,
but there are no promises around that.
This is kind of an experience.
So you can come in person without quality bets.
And historically, if you fall behind in terms of lecture,
which is what often happens with students don't come to lecture,
the other parts of the course is snowball
and become a lot more difficult.
So it really encourage you to come with your tenant.
Discussion and lab attendance aren't tracked,
and we're going to talk about what that counts for in a bit.
It doesn't directly count for your grades,
but it counts for something called participation points.
And then finally, all your assignments, labs,
home rates, projects can be submitted remotely.
So if you happen to be out of Berkeley for some reason,
or you have an emergency, as long as you look computer on you,
you should be fine.
OK, so as you mentioned earlier, with some of your tutors,
we also offer a small room tutoring section,
which are led by the staff that we saw earlier.
Local structures are around four of these people,
and it's just to be a more intimate environment
to review the material.
But these are from the optional, and there
are limited number of spots.
So around the end of this week, we'll have sign-ups.
And to make it more clear, the purpose of these sections
are, if in discussion, you feel like you
aren't getting enough review, and you would like more practice,
you can sign up for one of these tutoring sections,
you'll get more practice with supplemental material,
and a small environment, so maybe you can ask more questions
and feel more comfortable.
Those sign-ups will be up on this.
And in this week, I'm Piazza.
Also, we have something called conceptual office hours.
So I do think it all upstairs is a good session
in my training work.
But unfortunately, you're on a side of usually
that cloned with just to make a sign-up question
and debugging help, which is also useful,
but usually doesn't get to the core of the material,
the key constants that may test on your exams,
for example.
So conceptual office hours are a place that
are specifically reserved for no assignment help
and only conceptual questions.
So these will be out into the calendar scene,
and you can expect to go there for that type of help.
So girl is such a piece.
Historically, in this course, a combination
is because people can continue collecting every single day
and it's kind of a great decade.
It was student falls behind to whatever reason.
There's a great opportunity to catch
back up on materials that just pass, right?
Because we just keep going with new content.
Real sections are kind of meant to go this gap
because they'll be once a week.
They go from zero to a hundred of that little material
to a scaffolding worksheet.
Essentially, with a formatting, they'll go to this room
with a bunch of mixed units,
working to get some on the view on depth
as this is a big topic.
So it's doing it from cheering sections
and that you don't sign up.
They're going to be dropping.
You can go to one, you can go to all of them.
And at the bill section, you'll be in groups
and work through this gap with a worksheet
and hopefully by the end,
feel much more comfortable with those topics
that you might have missed earlier in the week.
Does that make sense to be ready?
Or any questions that I think I went through so far?
Yeah, that's fine.
Is the left task going to be real?
So I'm not going to go to the court as opposed to that.
For a court and a post it, Alex and Chris know more about it.
Yeah, so we're like, the reason we have so many microphones
is because we're recording it right now.
But to note, there's no guarantees on one
that screencast will go up.
It might be that evening, it might be a day or two later.
So that's, it's meant to help you review the lectures
if you missed something in live lecture,
but it's not meant to be a consistent replacement
for live lecture.
Cool.
Any other questions?
Yeah.
What answer?
We're going to be every Friday at 11 a.m.
So we have lecture, money,
you're freezing, real protection, but Friday, I think
it's still in the book or room,
but we'll have those details on the website too.
It won't start this week.
It will start like in the future.
Yeah, don't we know the real section this week?
They start second week.
Okay.
Are you missing at home?
Yes.
In the front.
Oh.
I mean,
it's going to look more and more carefully
to take the stage around it,
but more more more more.
They may change right.
Oh, yes, it turns from the fire, of course,
to the hands,
but I don't know if it's the one hand to the one
that won't be done at 18.
Yeah.
So the question was,
do the homework to change?
So the function has to be where it is.
We also do know if the project will change
by the way, doesn't look enough.
The homework will be so much different
because we're going in a different case,
the numbers will map,
but quite a few of the problems are shared.
I hope this has been getting at like,
ask your friends to introduce them up to you,
do you think?
You not do that.
Those are a lot of things,
but yeah, some of the homework problems
are similar to the past and that.
All right.
There's one more question.
Yeah.
So the realizations are 11 a.m. on Friday, two, what time?
11 1 p.m. on Friday.
Yeah.
Okay.
And we have more details up on Kiazza
once you have the room book
and one deception that for half of it.
Yeah.
Oh, can we come like half way?
So you're,
you're free to come half way, no one will stop you.
But it might, because we try to keep the group's pace,
it'll be a little bit harder,
possibly, but you're free to come,
just have that in mind that it'll be a little bit more
difficult to keep up and become half way.
Cool.
So let's go a little bit into disagreeing breakdown.
This is a graph of how your points are distributed.
There's more details on the website.
I don't want to get to it in the new shazits.
Just to note, 140 of your points are from the exams,
which we'll talk about in a bit,
and 150 of your points within the budget.
So it was a really the both of your points.
So it made you put the decision points earlier
from discussion and lab attendance,
participation points as you would have noticed
in that three graph, not here.
The reason for that is because they don't
explicitly count towards your final grade.
If you don't want to participate,
you could not participate in any lab discussion.
However, we don't really encourage that.
So if you're putting in effort,
if you go to every lab and every discussion,
if you happen to do below 50% of your exam,
your attendance and your participation points
will help you get closer to 50%.
So if you do above 50%, it won't help you at all.
If you do below 50%, it'll help you at closer.
The specific or mill we use for toppling this
is on the website, you can like 10,000 numbers
see the precise number of discussions
you want to go to, but ultimately,
I encourage you to just go to your discussions and labs.
The point of this is to give the credit
the people who are really trying the best in the course.
And for some reason, don't go to the exam,
but you will let everything out.
That'll make sense.
Any questions?
Does that make this patient?
Yeah.
Can you tell me if you're going to the school
or are you especially going to the lab
that we are involved in?
Yeah, you can get the patient credit going
to a different section, but for the first two weeks,
please try to put this section here in Golden,
just because we'll all be quite happy.
To be clear, the discussion section here in Golden
and the lab section that matches with that discussion section.
Yes.
Am I missing any?
Okay.
All right.
So another thing I'm reading,
there's going to be quite a bit of a new shift
for a next slide, five slides.
We're almost there.
Homer 3D is done because after.
What this means is that you don't be distressed
about getting the entire homework fully threatened,
especially some of the homework from this class
will be very challenging.
And we don't want you, that's your head.
If you're too bored because you can't get one or two problems.
Instead of how we do homework 3D is,
if you get the majority of the problems correct,
and we see some evidence of effort for the rest of the problems
I mean, you wrote a program, we have other metrics
for measuring whether you tried on our end,
but for your purposes, this means Google attempts
and all the problems getting most of them correct.
If you do this, you will get credit
for your homework assignments.
This means basically the point of this is knowing
you to be pressured to teach or look your friend's solution
at anything like that, because if you put in your effort,
keep up in the material, you should be able to get both
in on the homework just by trying on your problems
and getting most of them correct.
Any questions on this because I know
this might be able to confuse you?
Okay, other, yeah, in the front.
Or some of them are more than two lines of homework
so all of them come out of the network.
Yeah.
So we've got to be in the front,
some of the homework and a few lines of code,
only a few lines of code, how do you measure effort?
That's really good question.
So effort is definitely not writing a wall
and it's program possible.
That's not how programming works.
That's what it could mean.
We have evidence of all your methods.
So the reason I give you details is because this one
should be easy when you're trying to name the system
and that's not what we want.
The reason we don't be creative corrected
is trying to make it as easy and possible,
but just to give some transparency,
we have kind of our whole history of your homework.
We've seen when you started,
you see how many times you tried,
there's a lot of data there.
So we know, yeah, I hope that kind of answers the question.
But if I give you like a black threshold,
then you could all just, I don't know,
try making five submissions and then we're done with it
and that's not really the point.
I don't even know what to do with it,
but yeah.
I don't know what to do with it as you go through it
as well as the fact that what I don't do
are asking for asking to do it for us.
Yeah.
Oh, okay.
Good question.
So you won't know what you're correct.
That's a big deal.
All the homework's from autofrainers,
so you'll know what you're correct
as soon as you found the correct question.
In the front.
I don't think that seeing programming is good
to do around that first end,
you have to correct me as you do,
get out of the right answer, right?
Yeah, I'm correct, I'm correct.
I'm correct.
So you get a 100 and a 10.
If you read the about page,
we go more in depth into this.
It's kind of hard to explain in person,
so you should read that first
and then there are any questions.
Essentially, we'd be like to extract away
how the effort creating works to kind of open earlier,
but just trust that happens that the point is,
don't stress about getting all the problems correct,
but try all of them, get most of them correct.
All right.
So, you guys are seeing uncorrected and composition,
but you will get project partners.
So hopefully that lightens below in a bit.
Where you tell us that here,
and keep in mind that projects are pretty big,
it's the start one there, it actually posted.
Please don't put them off for the last minute.
Labs are also bringing on confusion,
but you get two labs jobs.
So we encourage you to put in your best effort.
We are gonna double check something.
Labs are great uncorrected, is right?
Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
Yes.
So, I've got the view both correct measurements,
but yeah.
So, we encourage you to complete all the labs
and try to finish,
and there are many to be assignments
that you can finish in the lab fully correct.
But if you end up having an off day,
you get one or two, not at 100%, it's okay.
You get two labs job.
More details, you have this website.
Okay.
So also we have slip days.
There are a lot of ways you try to introduce
community in the course, one is your one 24 hour slip day.
So this can be used on homework and projects.
We have, you know, final deadline,
officially on the course website,
let's say you have some emergency situation,
then you can use your slip day,
and submit a day later,
and you'll still get full credit.
But you can only do this one for this semester.
One thing to note is that,
let's say you have a project partner,
you use your slip hand off,
and then you partner up for dance,
which is on project three.
They have a slip day, but you don't.
If you both submit together a day later,
you're gonna get the late penalty, but they won't.
So that's an important thing to note.
Slip days are individual,
they can't be shared or gifted.
We don't agree, so sort of great economy in this class.
Okay.
And it's finally, these are the two of your exams.
Please make sure that your schedules are cleared.
Unless you have another class
with a directing van conflict,
we cannot offer an alternate.
So there will be a post for,
if you do have a class with a direct conflict,
how you can request an alternate,
that information will all be on Piazza,
but otherwise, please note the exam times.
Unless you have another class,
we cannot make exceptions.
All right, and now, let's just talk a little bit
about preparing for these exams
that feel like I've been deciding a lot of fear
about for the past, like 20 minutes,
because I just want to make it clear
that these exams are meant to be some sort of year.
They're not meant to be able to be scared.
The purpose of these exams are kind of like I mentioned earlier,
just is quite a few rental courts.
And the other types of the courts
tend to be a bit more practical,
especially your labs and your homework.
But in exams, to get asking questions
that get more to the core of specific concepts,
for example, share a person with a mental leader,
choose, I don't know how I'm only thinking
about you later, really, really in danger now,
but those are two big topics.
These are big concepts.
Sometimes when we don't enter them,
we have to ask, create a couple examples,
really get a sense of where you are
and showing your understanding.
So how do you say it's a new exam?
Generally, I think kind of this is a back down
for life courts and courts.
And this isn't maybe what worked for everybody,
but I want to give you my background.
And maybe the last one of you
to also explain how you did it,
just to give you perspectives.
For me, usually, at the end of the first week,
I decided to push a lot to classes.
I would look at one of the first exams
from maybe the past year or all of our exams
are posted on the resources page as soon as.
You can access them there and take a look.
What I'm trying to say is I would look at that exam
and then it'll look like complete gibberish community, right?
If I want to be able to identify
what are the terms that come up the most often?
What are the types of problems that come up on this exam?
And then later on, in lecture, in discussion, in lab.
But when I see that term again,
when I see that there's a problem,
I notice a super important.
And I also know the levels of importance.
And so once I've seen a couple of those problems,
I do like to now go back and try out those past exam problems.
Because I've seen them before and now you know
of a learn the material when they got to that part of the course.
What I'm trying to get at is just one approach.
Some people don't like this because if it's world exam,
in my experience, I don't remember
and then I looked at me once,
so it feels well for me.
But what I'm trying to get at is not putting off exam settings
to be told because that'll make it a lot more stressful.
If you try to pack an exam problem every week,
at the end of the week or the end of the fall week
after went through that material,
you'll find that it's a lot easier
to figure out how to approach them and master them
and create strategies to tackle them.
I also really urge you to talk to your staff
about this, the TA's, because they'll have
the experience of them being able to relate to you
more closely and you don't experience it.
I guess one of the things I'll mention
is that all the resources page,
as we get further into the course,
for every topic will have specific lists
of the past exam problems from that topic.
So that's another way to study.
You can go through, all right,
we just went through higher functions.
We'll leave on the resources page
and try the past exam problems or higher responses.
Yeah.
Alex also made this helpful flowchart.
So, what he is trying to believe here
is that you can start out with going to lecture
and then you can catch up with him, you can prefer that.
Then you go to lab, do some homework, go to discussion.
After that, he's no post-shaking on a concept.
That's what really sectioned it for.
Also tuning sections that you like.
And then after you have a foundation,
you should be ready to tell me
how those are naturally advanced.
It won't be difficult,
but the point of that little tooth
is that you do it over and over again.
I don't even know if you'd lecture in your test,
but I really want to encourage you to start early
and I think that'll really improve your experience.
Cool.
Any questions on the exams or the resources we have for that?
Yeah, you know?
We saw people asking about it.
Yes.
So, in here, there's no hours without,
you know, people preparing for exams work.
That's a good point.
So conceptual officers are,
they're kind of mentioned as purpose.
You go to conceptual office hours with past exam problems
and we're looking forward to helping you there.
You know what's good,
right?
They're office hours for sure.
You're free to do that as well.
Like a sexual or kind of specialized for this.
So yes, definitely a component.
Any other questions?
Cool.
I'm almost tired of these logistics.
I think this is the last slide.
Okay.
So just some stuff, an academic honesty
or put nicely collaboration.
So, this class is not clear.
They're acceptance.
This means that whether the 10 people next to you fail
because you, but I'm not going to admit to a scenario.
No one would happen to a student.
It's not going to change the green that you get.
So there's no incentive to do so, please.
So, instead, what you really want to call through this class
is an environment of collaboration, helping,
and sharing with one another.
We highly bridging work together
because really for me,
that's how we look at this class.
So my best friend was 16 one day.
Wow, it's used right here.
And that's really the point of this operation.
Policy, but there are limits.
One, you cannot share code as anyone else in the courts
except for your project partner
on a project that you're working together on.
The only circumstance, yeah,
where you can look at someone else's code
is what your partner is.
So, sharing code with you the means,
if you're sitting together in your dorm
and you look at someone else's dreams
and you want to help them, that's still sharing code.
And it's explicitly not allowed.
We've run into what businesses or people say
that's all they're doing
and that's how they ended up with exact copies.
And even if you go to 10 this such,
it often happens inadvertently when you're programming.
So, please do not look at anyone else's code.
We also have software for detecting this,
and we will find out what's likely to do it.
So, that's just a warning.
Sorry to get to your software.
Okay, so, if you wanted to just read anything I just said,
it's all on the website.
Chris, you're a very detailed documentation,
and now you can talk to Alex.
Okay, so now we're going to dive into
the content of the course.
The first thing we're talking about is expressions.
So, what are expressions?
So, expression describes a computation
and evaluates to a value.
So, this is some way we can kind of symbolically
represent or programmatically represent some sort of
computation that we're going to be doing.
The field of mathematics has done this for a really long time.
They have numbers.
They represent things in a bunch of different ways.
Some of the ways, you put two numbers.
You put a plus sign between them.
Here you have some other format.
You have some line between them.
Competition's really love notation.
Here you put some number.
You put some house over it.
You get another number.
Here you just put a word and you get another value.
So, here you can use another language, Greek,
and you just suddenly have another thing.
So, and there's a bunch of these.
Okay, so, mathematics has a lot of ways
that they like to describe things
because they like doing notation
and having really short hand in the research papers.
It's really hard to read.
In computer science, we really like to simplify things.
So, in computer science, the only thing
that we really care about is this one
a particular f of x.
What this is kind of saying
is that we're taking in some particular value
and we're going to manipulate it in some way.
Really general, it's really abstract.
Take something, change it.
The function f describes how we're going to change it.
The input x is just the particular value
that we care about.
I claim that every single one of these kind of expressions
or any other sort of expression
that we might think about in math,
that these can actually be represented
in this f of x notation.
And so, we're actually going to look at this in,
Python, would somebody be willing to hold this
since it isn't working?
I think we're going to download.
I put on a college shirt
because supposedly they work best,
but apparently they work worse.
Not me or sis?
Thank you.
Okay, so,
what I just did is I open me, this is just in Linux,
it's similar in Mac and Windows,
you'll probably use Git Bash.
If I went to open the Python interpreter,
I typed Python 3.
So what this is, is it's a looping mechanism
where we can type in things,
Python figures out what the means
and what I typed and then it returns the value.
So for example, I can type 2019,
it figures out what 2019 is,
there's nothing special and we output that.
The other thing we can do is we could do addition.
We can output some other values.
So here it's figuring out that we want to add to numbers.
It calculates the addition and then puts them together.
We can also do addition, we can do division,
we can do more addition, we can do nested equations,
we can do more multiple locations.
And it automatically knows the sort of standard
orders of operation and it'll sort of evaluate it
in the normal way that we're used to.
Another thing that we can do in the sort of functional
notation that I was mentioning is there's some built in
things that we can type.
So we can say max of two numbers.
It's going to return the value that it's a maximum.
The function notation just says,
okay, there's something that we want to call
and we're to separate these in parentheses
and put some commas between these things.
This is how Python more or less knows
that we're doing a function call.
We can do min, calculates minimum.
And this is great null, but I claim that we can do
everything in this function call notation.
Right here we're not doing this with the addition.
And it doesn't quite work that we can't just do this.
It's going to give some strange error
that doesn't quite make sense.
We actually have to do it, it's kind of the way
Python works, we have to run this line.
And this is kind of the underlying behavior
of how the addition and multiplication works
and it allows us to do this other format.
So we can now add things together,
we can multiply things together, let me.
And another thing we can do is if you've ever seen
in mathematics where we do multiple values
in a particular function,
we can actually just separate them in more commas.
We'll get more values.
We can also nest them, and it'll automatically figure out
the order of evaluation based on the nesting structure.
And so the nice part about using this call
expression notation is it's very clear what goes where.
We are going to evaluate the multiplication of 4 and 56
before we add to do it.
We're going to figure out what our validation is
before we max that in the other addition.
And sort of this nested structure makes it very clear.
In the first lines that we're doing,
you have to kind of know the order of operations
of mathematics, and maybe you're too lazy
and you don't remember that.
Having this sort of consistent notation
is very nice for program languages as well as computers
because it just follows a simple set of rules
and it'll figure out what it is.
Are there any questions about that?
All right, cool.
Thank you.
I don't know how to get back.
Maybe.
OK, so call expressions itself.
We're going to look kind of like how they're formatted
and how they work.
So a general call expression here, we're saying add 2 and 3.
This whole thing is what we call a call expression.
The way you kind of know there's the name of the function.
There's some parentheses.
There's some values separated by commas.
Some terminology we call add the operator.
This is the thing that we're operating on the values.
Add will do the addition.
And the other things are calling operands.
So operators apply to operands.
We're applying add 2 and 3.
In this case, it's not a particularly complex call
expression, but in the case that we saw in the demo,
we saw nested structures.
So each of these values can also be expressions themselves.
Instead of two, I could have said mole 5 and 6.
And I could have had some other value.
And it needs to sort of figure out these values
before it does this kind of application.
The exact way that Python goes about this
is the first thing it does is it sees this as a call
expression, it says, all right, I want to figure out
what this evaluates to.
So the first thing I'm going to do is figure out
what is the operator?
In this case, it's just looking up what add is.
It says, OK, this is some thing that does addition,
takes some numbers, and adds them together.
The next thing it does is it goes through each of the
operands.
These are the arguments that we're plugging in.
It figures out what 2 is, it figures out what 3 is.
Now that we've kind of figured out all these values,
and the reason why we're doing this is because in the case
I mentioned, if 2 is instead mole 4 and 5,
we have to figure out what 4 times 5 is before we can add
4 times 5 and 3.
Once we've figured out all these values,
we can actually do this application.
So we know what addition is.
We know what 2 and 3 is.
So now we can actually add 2 and 3 according to how
addition works.
By following this very precise sort of set of rules,
it allows us to understand how computers are going about
to calculate any arbitrary sort of value.
And because it's so simple, and it's these sort of three
relatively simple steps, computers can follow this
relatively quickly.
It says, all right, I don't have to really think about how
this is structured.
Do this step, this step, and then this step,
and I'll have the result.
So we're going to look at an example.
So it's add, we're adding 6 and 4 times 6 as well as 3 times 5.
So as people, the way we kind of approach this
is we look from the inside out.
The first thing that we're going to try and figure out
is what's 4 times 6.
We're going to get 24.
Now after this, we're going to add 6 and 24.
We're going to get 30.
We're going to multiply 3 times 5, 15, and add these together.
We're going to get 45.
So when I look at this, I can quickly say, OK, what's the
innermost call?
OK, it's 4 times 6.
So I should probably do that one first.
You can also imagine saying, OK, I'll actually do 3 times 5.
Then I'll do 4 times 6, and then I'll add them together,
as long as we're kind of building up through the levels.
Computers in Python can't quite do this.
It needs to have a specific set of rules.
And while we're kind of as people can look at the whole thing,
kind of jump around and do whatever we want,
programs need to follow a very specific set of rules.
The way we would do this in sort of the following the 3 steps
that we said before is we're going to follow these 3 steps.
If I like to operator, the operands and apply.
This is something that will be set a lot.
I'm probably in discussion as well as lecture.
And the process for this is here.
We see a call expression.
We're going to evaluate the operator.
In this case, it's just addition.
Nothing particularly complex.
The next thing is the operand.
We're going to add 6 and multiplication of 4 and 6.
We have to figure out what this is before we can actually
do the top level addition.
To figure out what this value is, we have to repeat the set.
Evaluate the operator.
Evaluate the operand.
In this case, it's 6.
So we just get 6.
And we repeat the process.
We evaluate the operator, the operand, and the operand.
Now for this sub-expression, mole 4 and 6,
we figured out the first 2 steps.
We've added, we figured out what the operator is.
We figured out what the operands.
We can now do this final step of applying things.
We can say multiplication 4 times 6, the 24.
We'll kind of go up this tree structure.
Because it's like branching out.
Then we'll say 6 plus 30.
Now to figure out the top level, we have to kind of go
through this again.
And so this is how computers are actually
going about solving these, like you've given instruction.
It says, all right, let's compute this value.
And this is a process that it's going through.
It says, first, let's look at the uppermost level.
All right, what are we looking at?
A call expression.
All right, let's look at the operator.
Let's look at the operands.
Let's kind of go through this structure
and to figure out all of the possible values.
And we kind of resolved ultimately what we're trying to do.
There's whole things called an expression tree,
where we have each of the things being the expressions.
And they break into sub-expressions.
And each of these evaluate to some particular value.
Are there any questions about this?
Cool.
And then we're going to do another demo.
Thank you.
OK, so a couple of concepts in this course
are functions, values, objects, interpreters, and data.
So you've seen the interpreter.
That's the type of interpreter.
We can type in things.
It evaluates things.
I mentioned functions like add and mole.
Values are like numbers.
And we'll see a little bit of objects in data.
In this demo, I'm going to be using some things
that we haven't taught.
But the point is not too confusing.
The point is just if we had to introduce all these concepts,
it would get to a cool demo in the first day.
So we want to do that.
So I'm just going to kind of do some things.
You aren't going to have to understand everything.
If you come back maybe later in this semester,
some of these might make more sense.
OK, so a long time ago, there is this author Shakespeare.
I have a file on my computer.
Actually, I think I need to.
Nope.
I misspelled Shakespeare.
All right.
Cool.
So what this is, is this is a text document with a bunch,
or I think all of Shakespeare's writings.
So we can get the particular values,
so we can read the data from this file,
and then we can split these into words.
This is going to be common.
OK.
So what is in this?
We go to the first 25 words, and we see the first play,
at least in this document.
And it's a very nice game.
That's the first words, and it tells the play itself.
OK, so we can ask Python how many words are in Shakespeare?
OK.
So there's 980,000 words in all of the text of Shakespeare.
If we're going to do this manually, it's take a long time.
But Python did this pretty quick.
So this is pretty impressive.
But let's actually take a closer look.
So let's ask, OK, how many of these words to Shakespeare write
are actually the word the?
So it turns out 23,000 of every word that Shakespeare wrote
is just the word that is.
So that's about 2%, something like that.
I don't think we can look at is, if you notice, in the first line,
we see a bunch of commas.
So because of the way I split this, commas are also considered words.
So let's actually look at how many commas there are.
So there's actually 81,000 commas just in Shakespeare.
So that's how many words are.
We can figure out exactly what percentages
by dividing this by how many words there are.
We get about 8% of Shakespeare's just commas.
And I think we do say, OK, there's a lot of repeats.
Clearly, there's a lot of does.
But maybe we're only interested in looking
at the particular unique words.
So the way we can do that is we can say, all right, only
with unique words from Shakespeare.
And now we can check, OK, is that in the words that Shakespeare has?
Yeah, so it is.
All right, how many words, unique words
does Shakespeare use?
OK, they have 33,000 unique words in Shakespeare.
That's a lot.
Another thing we can do is we can do some string manipulation.
So here, if I put this thing in quotes,
this is way Python says, all right,
we're just going to type this string of characters in a word.
Another thing we can do is we can actually reverse words.
So now it's word.
Oh, that's interesting.
John Ward are both actually words.
So maybe we can look in Shakespeare, which words are also
inside of their reverse.
So the way we do that is we're going to look over all the words.
You don't have to understand what I'm doing right here.
Yeah, OK, I guess that's a good point.
We're going to clarify the goal of this.
The goal is to show that Shakespeare has a lot of words.
And the power of computers, it allows us to go through things
automatically in order to see a lot of analysis and sort of data
that would be really painful to do manually.
Computers do this almost instantly and basically instantly.
Well, if we were to do this manually, you'd take a long time.
And so we can leverage the power of computers
to sort of do this analysis on data, which
was the other topic in this course.
We've also seen sets, which are actually objects.
And you can make believe these.
We'll kind of cover each of these concepts
that I mentioned a little bit more in depth throughout the course.
OK, so here, I'm looking at all the words that are also
the reverse of the words.
So this is going to be palindroms, I guess.
So we see all of the palindroms and Shakespeare, which
are length greater than four, or these ones.
So writer is also a writer, level is level.
One of the thing we can do is we can look in Shakespeare.
Maybe we only care about if the word is actually also in the words.
So here, we're looking at all the words of length four,
that when you take the word, you reverse it.
It's also in Shakespeare.
So let's see, there's, I don't know if these are words.
I'm not quite.
OK, gums and smug.
Oh, snug.
Oh, no, these are words.
OK, move and pull.
Yes, OK.
This is why I guess the computer science major.
OK, we can also look at length five.
So we have some more.
We can look at length six, all right.
There's still some more.
Are there seven?
So there's no more.
Are there any more greater than seven?
OK.
So we're kind of in our adoptions.
And the reason for this is Shakespeare didn't use all of the words
of the English dictionary.
We can also actually load in, let's see.
I need to figure out the document.
So on my computer, I have a file.
You don't have to understand this.
OK, so now I've loaded in the dictionary of all of the words
on my computer, at least in this one dictionary.
So now, look at the length of words, there's now 102,000.
So originally we had, I think, 30-ish,000.
So we've increased the number of words by a lot.
So we can do things like, OK, what
is the longest word in this list of words or a set of words?
We can take all the words.
We can say, all right, what I care about
is the length of these.
OK, so this is the longest word in the dictionary.
Oh, I'm not going to try to pronounce that.
We can also look alphabetically.
We can say, OK, what's the last word in the dictionary alphabetically?
We get it toads.
Let's see, what else can we do?
We can go back to the original thing we had.
We're saying all the words, which also have reverses in it,
which are length 6.
So we see there's a little bit more words.
And then we can, again, are there
anyone's greater than 6?
So in this case, we actually have more of these.
So stressed and desir, desir, oh, OK, OK, so we can actually,
for example, we could say, OK, what is the largest word?
Such that.
So we're looking at the longest word
in this set of words, such that the reverses in it.
And we get stressed and desir.
Cool.
OK, so this is kind of all I have for this.
Are there any other things you guys would be interested in looking at
what we could do in this sort of data set?
Maybe like looking up words that are, I don't know,
are there any ideas?
Yeah.
How many words start with A?
OK, so we could take how many words, if the first letter is A?
So 4,600, so many things.
And then I think, yeah, so some of these, let's say,
let's say, this, except now, we're going to look at that for.
OK, so 6,000 words, ignoring capitalization, start with A.
Any other guess?
Yeah.
Is there a simple way in it?
So instead, in that stop-up, I mean,
that's stressed and dessert is another thing,
versus avoiding A, so that those between ones won't be there.
So we only care about, so if there's a word like stress,
you don't care about the inverse of it.
Yeah, so in other words, you can do that is back in this one.
Not this one.
So another thing we can say is, I can't hear a people if you want this
too.
Oh, yeah.
Thank you.
He asked, is there anything we could exclude the reverse of the
word?
So we got stressed, but maybe we don't want desserts as well.
Or maybe we want desserts, but not stressed, if you don't
want to reverse.
So the way you can do that is we can say, and we only care
about the one that is actually smaller alphabetically.
So we get two of them.
Cool.
So this actually excluded palindromes.
We can actually say less than or equal if we care about palindromes.
Cool.
Because deified is also the reverse.
Yeah.
How is the number that's not had out for this?
Do you know what that is?
That's what that is.
That's what the word is.
Um, I'm interested in what are the words that
store the capital H or the lower key say?
This might elucidate something.
There's a lot.
Oh, so the reason why is let's look at...
So some of these words like arctic also have the capitalization.
So when we lowercase them, we don't care about the ones
that we're also duplicated.
Any other ideas?
Yeah.
Most number of vowels.
Okay.
So we can say, um, we're going to max over the words, uh, you
don't need to know what this means, uh, I'm going to say...
But you will see.
You'll be able to understand all of this.
Yes.
And we want to, um, uh, one for W in X if, uh, let's see, uh,
so this is the word that has the most, uh, like the word that has the most, uh,
the most repeating single letter, um, so we can say, we want the maximum word where the
key is equal to, well, okay, so we can do it with a specific vowel.
So if I said which one has the most ease, we get teleconference, it's a X, which one
has the most X's, X ons, not quite sure how you do with all of the letters, though.
Yeah, you'd have to kind of go through all the letters and then get the maximum over
all of those.
So we'd have to sit here and type a long string with the whole alphabet.
We could do it, but it'll take a while.
Oh, yeah, he's saying like, um, he's saying to the subtract the set of unique letters
from the length of the word, um, because then you'll have a, but like, I think that that
version, right?
So if you have two letters that both repeat a lot, you want to certainly get the one word
with the most repeats of the same letter, right?
Like, okay, basically the probably isn't easy way to do this, but we don't know if the
top of our head, but I think that approach would, I mean, yeah, you could say, oh, my
God, okay, so I'm iterating over all the letters and I'm saying, and now it's intact.
Oh, no, I don't need this, nope, generics, oh, okay, I see, I have the most A's, I guess,
wait, that's like not that many A's, I think maybe it's a lot of A's, yeah, I guess I
guess it's a lot of A's, yeah, use a regular expression, maybe, I'm not very good at
regular expression, okay, cool, yes, I can hold it up for you, cool.
So I guess the purpose is going to show you some neat things you can do in Python, you
can actually download the Shakespeare text, it's in the textbook, I think it's one of the
first links, if you go to the 1.1 chapter, if you want to mess around with it yourself,
it's just kind of show you the neat things you can do in Python, what kind of moving on
to some other kind of building up and maybe by the end of the semester, you kind of understand
all the specific things that we've done and how you might approach these for yourself.
Anyway, tomorrow, thank you all for coming, we'll be up here if you have any questions.
Thank you.