So today we're going to be doing a software engineering lecture.
This is a somewhat of an experiment.
So I'm going to give you some backscorian why it's happening.
So an interesting note that in 2003-ish and earlier,
61A had two days a week, Monday,
Wednesdays of technical topics,
and then Friday was always something else.
Now sometimes that was some social implications thing
where we talk about the impact of computing.
And it was a way before I was like your age at the time.
But they would talk about alternate topics, whatever it may be.
You get guest speakers, whatever else.
But over time, 61A's content grew and grew
until social Fridays, as I believe they were called,
disappeared entirely.
So what I'm trying this semester is I'm
going to bring this back a little bit in 61B.
Where for three weeks, I'm going to dedicate this class
to these sorts of topics.
So to be a different flavor of lecture,
it'll be less technical.
It's not going to be we have this old computation problem.
Let's try and solve it together.
It's going to be generally a little bigger.
Now these are untested lectures.
Maybe they'll be good.
Maybe they won't be.
So do let me know what you think.
So some motivation for today is that if you think
about your education at Berkeley so far,
doing programming, we've misled you a little bit.
In 61A, a lot of the projects and homework
were filled in the function, where there's already a function.
You just have to write the code to make it do the thing.
And that's great for learning how programming works.
And even for finding and identifying sub-problems,
but it's not quite real world coding practice, sometimes.
Now in 61B, we've zoomed out a little bit.
And we said, we'd like you to build a class,
say, an extrinsic min pq or whatever.
And you're supposed to do it according to our spec.
We kind of kicked off the training wheels
and the projects as we went, taking away our autograder
and so forth, occasionally.
But I think it's fair to say that everything we've done,
even project 2C, is all at a small scale.
I mean, 2C, you're going to have this giant code base.
You're not touching most of it.
Most of it's just mysterious.
You can go look at it.
But it's not really something that you
have to interact with deeply.
Now, because you've always been working at a small scale,
you have built habits that may cause you great pain
if you build your own projects or whatever else in the future.
So in these lectures, among other things,
I'm going to give you a sense of how
you would deal with large scale, where
you're trying to actually build huge systems
from scratch where you're designing everything.
Though I will note that in lecture, it's actually very hard
to do this, because it's tough to find something
that's small enough to fit into lecture.
But it's large enough to showcase where
these issues are problematic.
I gave it a shot with an exercise.
We'll do at the end of today's lecture, but we'll see.
So project 3, that's where you'll have some breathing room.
This is after bear maps.
This will be a chance for you to actually design something
totally from scratch.
And you will feel the pain of the complexity
as you realize that you're boxing yourself
in the corner with short-sided decisions.
So I hope that these lectures help you, at least,
in some vague way.
But this is one of the very hardest topics
to teach you computer science.
169 is another place where you can get a taste of this,
or if you go and do internships.
So we'll see how it goes.
Now I should note that these lectures would not be possible
or they wouldn't be nearly as good if I did not
have this book.
So I had a former TA K. Osterhout who
was a grad student here.
And her dad is a computer science professor as it happens.
And he wrote this book.
So if you want to check it out, I think it's pretty good.
It's very high level, though.
It's a high level description of where you run into trouble.
And so I'm borrowing heavily from this book.
I want to give credit where credit is due.
And it's cheatbook.
All right.
So let's try it out.
So you've heard me say before that complexity
is your opponent, your enemy, and computer science.
And so I'm going to try and define complexity.
And I'm going to use John's definitions,
because I think they're pretty good.
Now, funny story.
Part of the activity here ever heard of the text editor
project that existed in 61B, some of you.
So let's bring 2016.
We did a text editor project where I had you guys
as the big, open, and did project build a GUI-based text
editor like Sublime Text, but much smaller.
And it's, again, these challenges,
the ones where we have you build something from scratch
are all about you hitting the black city
and feeling a little bad about it.
Now, that project was particularly tricky.
And since K was my TA at the time,
she told her dad, who teaches software engineering,
about this project.
And so he ran it not in an intro course,
but in an upper division software engineering course,
and he found it very interesting to see the mistakes
and strange errors and design decisions
that people made in building their text editor.
And in fact, indirectly, if you read in here,
there's some talk about that text editor project, which
is a descendant of our own.
So we're kind of going full circle here.
Anyway, so the point of this is he and I and others
out there teaching computer science,
we know that students grapple with complexity
and as a result of these kind of studies,
not just the text editor project in his class,
but his entire career.
He's another generation older than me.
He's come up with some definitions of complexity
that resonated with me, but these are by no means universal.
So to start understanding like complexity
is such a special problem in computer science,
it's actually kind of a great lecture for visitors,
by the way, if you have to know anything.
Anyway, so unlike other engineering disciplines,
like I don't know chemical engineering or whatever else,
software is not constrained by physics.
I mean, it is a little bit, because our computers only
run so fast and have so much memory.
But for the most part, you don't have
to think explicitly about that.
Now, as a result, when you try to build the system,
when you're programming, it's an act of almost pure creativity.
So chemical engineers, when they're dealing with building
systems, they have to think about messy things
like temperature.
If I run these reactions, there's latent heat that gets
built up, and I have to deal with getting rid of that heat.
It restricts what you can do, because there's physics.
Material scientists, they have to think about how brittle
the material is in order to recommend it for use in,
I don't know, airplane window shades or whatever.
And civil engineers need to worry about, say,
the strength of concrete if they're building bridges.
These things are very important.
And they have to deeply understand them.
And there's math, where we deeply look at the properties.
The tensile strengths of various materials,
we don't really have that in computer science so much.
We kind of do, but it's not nearly as deep
and as reflective of some physical world that we're limited by.
So instead, the limitation is not the materials
that we are working with, or the physical universe
around it, but it's our own brains.
It's the fact that we're not smart enough
to understand really complicated systems.
So the only limitation in terms of what
you're capable of achieving is being
able to understand what you're doing, which
is a very unique and interesting space.
Mathematics is kind of similar.
Mathematics is a purely creative discipline,
but it's not quite as directly applicable,
because there's no machine that brings
to life what you're building.
But at computer science, we have math that kind of lives.
And now, in the modern era, of course,
we've seen that it's very financially lucrative
and impactful on society to be able to do this.
Now that there's an internet, it's kind of insane
how the mathematical ideas you come up with
can deeply impact how people spend their time
or what's going on in the world.
So the limits of what it's possible to do at this point,
especially now that we have the internet,
is just what you are capable of fitting in your brain.
So the enemy then is complexity.
Our limitation is we are trying to understand
the systems that we want to build.
And what you'll observe, especially,
so in this class, you usually build a program.
You submit it to an autograder.
You make 30 changes, and you have get commits
that are like, help, please, help, please, please, help, whatever.
And then you push it.
And then you never touch that code again.
It's very different than the real world.
If you were to take those programs that you did
that committing style with, they would eventually
get so burdened and ugly under all those little changes
you made that they become painful.
So as programs are worked on over periods of months or years,
which you never ever do in these courses,
well, they gain more features, and they gain more complexity.
And over time, if you have a group of people working,
it becomes harder and harder to understand
what pieces you need to know about in order
to make modifications.
If you have hundreds of classes and they all interact
in complex ways, then adding a new feature
that, for example, lets the user animals
scroll around or something, maybe very hard.
You don't even know where to start necessarily.
Now tools like IntelliJ, which we've used,
or JUnit, or the IntelliJ debugger, or the Visualizer,
they make it easier to grapple with complexity.
When you have it, you can use these things
to extricate yourself from problems that you fall into.
But actually, the most important thing you want
to do in real software is to keep it simple.
So let's try and define this a little more.
So I'll start, I guess, just by mentioning
ways that you might try to keep complexity under control.
So one approach is to keep your code, well, as it's simple,
and what John uses the term obvious.
So you don't want special cases.
We saw that already creeping in early, early, early
in our class when we were building SLists.
So we hit a case where there was a problem where our code
crashed, and we tried to do add back.
And we could add an if statement that candles the null root,
or a null front node case.
Instead, we could also create a Sentinel node.
It's another approach.
Another is encapsulation into modules.
These are the two ways that he says you keep your code
under control.
So one is make it simple and obvious.
And the other is encapsulate things.
Put them in modules where you can hide information.
So that the creator of one module, let's say bear maps,
can use other modules like kdtree or a star solver
or whatever else.
And they don't have to know how they work.
All they need to know is the API.
These are incredibly important pair of practices
that if you go to any real-world project,
there will be the two techniques, the two levers you can
use to keep things under control.
This means there's less stuff to think about.
And this means the things that you need to think about
are small, they fit in our tiny working memories.
So what is complexity then?
How do you define this phenomenon?
Well, Osterhote defines it as follows.
He says complexity is anything related
to the structure of a software system that
makes it hard to understand and modify the system.
So it's a human-centric definition.
It's saying, however hard it is for a human to deal with the system,
to interact with it, to modify it, that's what matters.
We don't really care necessarily how complicated
it is just sitting on the shelf.
But if we ever need to change it again,
then that's we're going to run into trouble.
So complexity takes on a lot of forms.
So for example, understanding how the code works.
If you need to modify a piece of code,
you have to be able to look at it and know what it's doing.
It takes into account, for example, the amount of time
you need to make small improvements.
So like, oh, well, the font size sucks.
I don't like it.
How do I fix that?
Well, in some systems, that's easy.
There's some config file.
I just change some number to 26 or whatever.
And now it's bigger.
In others, maybe you have to do something crazier.
Like, go dig in the source code, modify a number
and recompile whatever it may be.
Another is just being able to find what needs to be modified.
I mean, that's closely related to the above idea.
And another is if it's difficult to fix one bug
without introducing another, which happens in code,
where your code has so many interdependencies
that changing anything breaks something else.
So it goes on to say that if a software system is hard
to understand and modify, then it is complicated.
If it is easy to understand and modify, then it is simple.
So he has a cost view of complexity, which
is that, I mean, another sort of not a different definition,
but a different way of thinking about complexity
is you can think of it as follows.
In a complex system, it takes tons of effort
to make even small changes.
But in a simple system, big improvements
require less effort.
So I'm going to give you an example.
You guys remember Katie Trees, Project 2B.
And I gave you guys some pseudo code that
looked a little like this.
So we had a nearest helper method.
And what it does is you give it a node, which
is the root of a Katie tree, or maybe a root of a sub tree.
We have a goal point, the thing we want to find.
And we have a best point, which is our best known point.
And the code is that this is the pseudo code as follows.
So we say, if the node is null, we don't have anything better.
So let's return best.
If the distance of the goal from the current node
is better than the distance to best,
well, then I'm going to reset my best pointer.
And then we're going to say, OK, we have a good child
and a bad child.
So we'll figure out which one's good and bad.
Then we search for good and the bad child,
and we return best.
So this approach I'd say is simple in the sense
that if you understand this pseudo code,
you know the basics of 61B, and you build code that looks
like this, it's going to be relatively easy to work with.
So a question for you.
Something's actually missing here.
I'm going to let you guys try and find it.
I'm going to answer it.
See if you can find the thing that is missing.
Yeah, I heard someone say, OK.
Yeah, remember that pruning rule.
So what's missing?
Let's see.
Types are changing and professor hugs the world.
All right, cool.
So what's missing is what?
The pruning rule, what do we need?
We need to say what?
So there should be an if statement here
that I'm just going to write out in English.
It basically just says, if there could possibly
be something better on the bad side, then do the search.
Now I've written this out narratively,
but it is possible the right code
that is reflective of this narrative.
And that's the glory of programming,
that it can actually read like a story, if you do it right.
So let me show you an example of a Katie tree
that is too complicated.
This is not for many students this semester.
In fact, it's from not even our class, but it's related.
So here's a different way to implement the nearest method,
in a Katie tree.
So this is a little different than what we showed.
It's not the same helper method.
But just briefly looking at it,
we can see that it is much more complicated.
It's doing something kind of similar.
So we have if is vertical, then do these things.
Otherwise, do these things.
There's a search here, and there's a check left variable.
We've got this is an L statement that has to do
if it's not vertical.
When this case we search, and then we say we should check
the right, then we have a check left variable,
then we go on to have some other stuff
that if we check left, and if it's vertical,
then we'll do the Euclidean and so forth.
And so, I mean, if you had to describe in a few words
what feels bad about this, like what is,
I don't know, I'm kind of curious,
how you would try and describe this in English.
Sure.
There's a lot of redundancy here, right?
This notion of check left, check right,
being set to true, like, I mean, at least it's narrative
in the sense that we're specifying what it is we're going
to do, it's not like do X or whatever.
So that's like the names, but there's redundancy.
And then, else there are other ways you might put it.
Yeah.
Yes, it's hard to read, hard to stave, it's correct.
And so, what about it?
I mean, other than redundancy or any other phrasing
about what feels bad about it, yeah.
Yeah, that's a really great point.
If you want to expand this to a third,
like you have X, you now have Z coordinates as well.
Well, because we have this Boolean that is vertical,
let's say we wanted to now have three levels.
Well, we could change that to an integer,
but you can see this code won't generalize well.
We would have to have an if statement for the X,
the Y, and the Z, and so forth,
and we would need to have God knows what.
So it seems like it gets more complicated.
Expanding on this code is nightmarish.
I'll be thoughts that occur to you.
Yeah.
Yeah, so say you find a bug.
Uh-oh, you know, this should be,
like this should be Y and this should be X.
I now need to go through every piece of code
and swap that everywhere,
and it's going to be really hard for me to keep track of it.
Maybe by the time I get eight lines then,
I'm like, oh, wait, should I have changed this one
because it's a slightly different case than they want above.
So this code is very hard to modify
if you find there's any bugs,
or if you decide to make it better in some way.
So for example, the pruning rule, in this case,
it was basically just a line,
and my kd tree solution looks almost like this,
where it really is just an if statement,
somewhere that changes the behavior.
Here, trying to get rid of the pruning rule
is so complicated.
The pruning rule, it's like roots all grown through it.
This is like a weed, if you've ever dug them up
in a garden where it's all grabbing your actual plants.
You know, God, what am I going to do?
This plant's so cool, but this is standalone growing through it.
Very upset about it.
Like this, the pruning rule is baked into every aspect of the code.
It permeates all of it, and that's dangerous.
Any other thoughts?
Yeah. God, it says verbose.
Can you give me some examples?
Like, yeah, it feels maybe a little strange
to have check right and check left.
And I think that's because of the framing or the abstractions
that the author used, they were kind of stuck with them.
But yeah, I agree.
That seems like that's more stuff you have to keep track of.
That if I'm using the debugger,
now I have to need to think about this check left
and check right variable.
And it could have maybe just been called something
like check other, or I don't know what,
but probably downstream that becomes complicated.
Interesting thought.
Other thoughts?
Yeah.
Yeah, so many cases, so many statements
that have become hard to reason about.
And indeed, yes, that's a, and that's sort of redundant
with an observation that's redundant,
but I think it's a great observation.
Yeah.
Yeah, trying to understand the intent of the author
is really hard.
They came at this cold.
Like, here's a great example.
Let's say that you're a TA at office hours.
And somebody says, my code's not working.
Here.
And then they want you to start explaining the whole piece of code.
There's, I mean, we could do it, but it would take you
perhaps an hour to explain what you were thinking.
And if the problem is that you did this,
there's no way that a TA.
No TA will ever, ever find that.
It's not possible.
That's another reason.
It's hard to communicate, get help, whatever else.
Yeah.
There's little code coverage.
What do you mean by that?
It's not a term we've used.
Yeah, so only some of the if conditions will be active at once.
Why do you feel like that's a problem?
Just to get some sense.
So if you're trying to maybe identify errors or fail like it
was correct, yeah, there's just so much to think about.
So many different conditions that need to be considered.
Great.
OK, these are all reasons.
So this right here, you may have produced programs like this
is fine.
I mean, I've written terrible programs,
especially when I first started writing code.
And even now, I still produce code that's bad, usually when
I'm in a hurry.
And that's just how it goes.
And we'll talk about that a little more.
Here's another example of overly complex code.
So this right here is a SNAP program.
This one of my former TAs, or my former students in CS10.
This is in the SNAP programming language.
Who took CS10 here?
Cool.
Hi friends.
What's up?
Anyway.
So CS10 is your first dose of programming.
And in that class, it is all about getting things just to work.
So you've never seen this language many of you.
But I'll give you a sense of what's going on here that's surprising.
So look at this.
Even if you don't know the language,
what seems maybe a little funny about this block of code?
So it's an if statement, which is if this and this, and this, and this, and not this,
and not this, and so forth.
This is a lot to look at.
And you can imagine as a novice programmer,
this is an implementation of the game battleship.
So it's like if ship hit is true, and down is true, and right is true, and up is true,
and left is true, and num is less than 91, who knows what that means?
That seems very hard to understand.
Oh, and not.
It's some item of a, I mean, it's hard to even imagine what it means, right?
Now this student, by the way, is now 186 TA.
So now four years later, they are graduating.
They started here with this code.
This is how they used a program.
But now they're running a pretty sophisticated upper division course.
That's one of the 20-hour TA's.
So I bring this as an example up, because in this case, this is not a large and sophisticated
system.
It's just complicated in the sense that it is just impossible to imagine trying to find
a bug in this code, or change it in some way to fix it, like, though, just especially
interesting.
Numb less than 91, I have to ask them what that means.
All right, snap, by the way, it's a great programming language.
I enjoy it a lot.
And let's you do recursion, but visually.
Anyway, all right.
Now one last little note about complexity in its definition.
So it also depends in John's view on how often a piece of code is modified.
So a system may have a few pieces that are highly complex.
Like, for example, it has like a Rungo CUDA solver for like ordinary differential equations,
because it needs to simulate some thermodynamic yada yada, right?
But if nobody ever really looks at that code, then the overall impact on the complexity
of the system is minimal.
So he says, if you want, you can write it out as a math equation.
So we could say that the total complexity is the complexity of each part times the time spent
on each part, say, where time is like someone needs to maintain the ordinary differential
equation solver or whatever.
We just sum that.
So if there's pieces that are rarely modified, but are highly complex, maybe that's
OK.
Just the thought.
All right.
So we're good.
I mentioned.
I was kind of cute.
OK.
You guys have some insight into this, but I'll tell you what, first, I'll tell you some
symptoms.
I'll tell you some causes, and then I'd be kind of curious to hear some anecdotes of
anybody has any.
So Osterhote, he describes three symptoms of complexity, signed to your code as becoming
bad, complex.
So the first is change amplification.
So if it's the case that a simple change requires you to modify lots of pieces, then
your code's getting complicated.
So that bad kd tree we saw earlier was an example of that.
If I needed to change anything, I'd have to do it in lots of places.
And this happens whenever you, for example, say, oh, well, I have this case, and then I'm
going to copy and paste it somewhere else, and I have two copies of the method, which is
like some minus sign flip, or whatever.
That's an example of complexity creeping into your code.
Another is cognitive load.
So this is how much you need to know in order to make some kind of a change.
Now, this is not the same thing as the number of lines of code.
It's often the case that more lines of code is simpler, because it's more narrative.
That's why I often define variables on one line, and then use them elsewhere.
You can do it in one line, but I find the code much simpler if it has a name.
In some cases, you may incur a small performance hit, but in modern compilers and Java,
that stuff mostly gets optimized out anyway.
Incidentally, someone asked, why don't we use plus plus or minus minus on Piazza recently?
So you can do it, but you'll notice I often use plus equals one.
The reason I don't really like plus plus is because it allows you to do things like,
well, comment this out.
So it allows you to do things like return x plus plus, whatever.
So if x is some variable, this says I want to both increment and
calculate the result of x plus one.
And I'm going to return the value before the change actually happens.
So that's something that's comprehensible to humans.
I just said it so fast that you didn't really get a chance to digest it.
So it's not so crazy, but I still think that it introduces a new possibility
where bugs can arise.
And actually, one thing that I really wish I had done,
especially inspired by homework four, is change the setup for IntelliJ so
that using equal equals versus dot equals was some kind of very glaring warning.
Because I know who here had that hop into them on homework four out of curiosity.
Yeah, we're used equal equals, and then you spend hours of your life realizing,
oh, so next semester, maybe I'll set up an IntelliJ warning.
Yeah, yeah, a lot of them.
You know, so, incidentally, that's why I find plus, plus difficult.
That's actually an example of cognitive load to some degree.
That's the idea that it's just more stuff to think about.
And one of the reasons I really like Java as a programming language is the static
types constrain your thinking.
When you go back to writing Python code, if you happen in a while,
you'll feel a little like it's like scary.
It's like waking up on the beach in the middle of a night, you know?
You're like, how did I get here?
You don't know where anything is.
There's functions, they're giving you stuff.
You don't know, it just feels bad to me.
And every time I come back to a statically typed language, I feel like I'm home.
All right.
Reduce this cognitive load.
Then the last he describes as something known, he calls unknown unknowns.
Now, this is a bit of a slippery definition that I will say I don't fully understand,
but he says it's the worst type of complexity.
The difference here is that unknown unknowns are when it's not even clear what you need
to know in order to make modifications.
Now, I can certainly appreciate that, where I have downloaded some tool,
actually somebody came to my office hours, who was working on a tool to do gaze tracking.
So for people who can't move their arms and legs, it's hard to use a computer,
but not impossible, because most people can still move their eyes.
So you can look around, you can blink.
And if you have a camera tracking somebody's eyes,
well, then they can actually manipulate the physical universe around them,
because they can look around blink in certain locations.
And in principle, it's possible to control a mouse cursor.
And if you're somebody who has locked into that degree,
it's quite freeing to be able to interact with the world,
even if it's kind of low bandwidth, it's better than nothing.
And so the student who I was talking to in office hours said,
how do I take this very complicated open source gaze tracking software
and make it that I can click when I blink?
And here, it's actually, I mean, this is not a flaw with the software system,
but just the fact that it's a difficult task, there's a significant unknown unknown.
How do you take this thing and somehow control the mouse cursor?
And that's something that's very difficult to grapple with in systems.
All right.
So what about good systems?
What features do they have that help us avoid these symptoms?
Well, the main one I love this term is that he says,
the system should be ideally obvious.
So in a good design, the system is obvious.
And in an obvious system, to make a change, you can easily, quickly understand
what you need to change, how you understand how the code works.
And if you want to do something like change the font size
or make it so that the user doesn't have to log in every 15 days,
but only every 30 days and whatever.
They're two factor authentication or whatever.
Then ideally in an obvious system, it's just easy.
They don't have to think about it.
And what's more is that they should feel pretty good that the change will work,
even though they don't read much code.
So examples of this would be you have a table of constants
and you just go into the constants that are well labeled and you say instead of 1530.
That's an example of an obvious system.
So why are systems not obvious?
Where does complexity come from?
Well, I should note that every software system starts up beautiful, pure,
and clean.
It's just a blank file.
The problem is, though, that as you work with code, it slowly gets uglier and uglier.
And this is almost an inevitable feature of every program I have personally ever written.
And what happens, basically, is that you introduce these little complexities
a bit at a time.
And some complexity is inevitable, right?
And if you're building a system that's able to track the gaze of a human being,
it is going to have some complexity to it because that's just inherently a complicated task.
Now, what happens, though, as you build a software system is that you make these hundreds
or thousands of small dependencies and obscurities that are going to build up over time.
And eventually, there's going to be so many small issues that every possible change
is affected by a lot of them.
So this incremental process of creeping complexity is why it's so hard to keep complexity under control.
You've done this when you're writing programs, where you're working on it,
you're adding little bits of changes to fix some corner case.
And eventually, your code becomes, well, I mean, it turns into this kd tree, right?
This author didn't set out to write something like this.
But as they added pieces, it's like, what could go back and refactor?
But I know if I just add another if statement.
I think I'm pretty sure it'll work.
So Osterhote says, rather than ever, ever, ever letting yourself do this,
you should have a zero tolerance philosophy.
And I think that's actually a good message when you're building real software.
Arguably not reasonable in the middle of a semester when you're busy.
But hey, it's a good strategy for the real world.
So I'm rounding out some thoughts.
And we're going to do a little exercise too.
So let's talk about what he calls strategic versus tactical programming.
So out of all the programming you've ever done, I'd say that it's pretty much all
tactical.
So your goal was to get something working, like introduce a new feature or
fix a bug, like this is what you do.
So that may seem like kind of a silly criticism because having code that works
is a good thing.
Like why is it bad to optimize for working code?
And you can probably see this coming.
But the problem is that if you do this, you don't spend time thinking about
the design.
And you introduce these little complexities.
Like I need two copies of a method that do similar things.
And every one of those complexities always feels fine, right?
You're like, this is going to make my code work.
They'll do this extra thing.
But eventually when you do work on these problems, you start to feel the weight.
You could step back and fix it.
The author of Katie Tree here could have stepped back and changed things up.
But why don't you?
Well, because you just need to make a few more changes that you could submit
the autograder and then you could do everything else that you want to do in your life,
right?
So the problem, if you take that with you, forwards, and maybe even now while
you're working on projects, is that you end up building so much complexity into
your system that you can't really keep track of it.
And eventually, you end up adding even more complexity to deal with the original
complexity in its no balls.
So in project three, good news, I will give you a chance to build something big
enough that you will feel the complexity creeping.
Because you're going to build something from scratch and you should see it and feel this
menacing complexity.
Now, the good news is that the system is just small enough that I think you can get
through it without a bad time, but you will feel the bad time all around you.
OK?
All right.
So there it gets kind of like painting yourself into a corner and then like tossing
them with your landmines.
And then you can quit and you don't have to worry about it again.
OK.
Yeah.
Oh, yes.
Thank you.
Cool.
All right.
Go back.
OK.
All right.
Anyway.
No luck.
Mysterious.
Right.
Let's do that.
OK.
Hold on.
Yeah.
I meant to.
We were making the slides animated earlier, but they didn't show up.
OK.
Let's go.
Project 2C is out.
Let's do it on when we have any visitors for Cal Day.
Oh, good.
No.
OK.
I got to scroll back over.
Is it worth it?
Anytime we'll find out.
That's fine.
OK.
Let's see if it happens.
Whatever.
All right.
So it goes on to say that rather than be tactical, the first step, OK?
Maybe there's one sentence that I want you to take home today.
The first step towards becoming a good software designer is to realize
that working code isn't enough.
Actually, what really matters when you're building real software, not necessarily 61A,
B or C or whatever other projects, but when you're building real systems that need
to last, the most important thing is the long-term structure of the system.
Because getting it working, I mean, it might take an extra day or two to get it.
Working if you're building things out in this strategic and carefully thought out manner,
but you will get much better benefits in the long term.
He also says, though, that again, never he has this zero tolerance policy,
which I think is a great idea, and I try to keep that with me when we build
graders.
I feel like our autorator infrastructure is generally pretty good.
Doesn't break on a fundamental level.
Though, the homework for autorator was definitely done tactically.
Sorry.
Anyway.
Strategic programming, of course, takes lots of time investment, and again,
it will seem mysterious and hard, but Project 3 will have you a chance to
give you a chance to see what's going on.
So we give you a couple suggestions.
It feels like it's going a little long now.
I hope you're still enjoying it.
So it goes on to say that, I mean, this is my interpretation, so I agree with this.
So when you're actually building something out, what do you do that's better?
Well, rather than, I think this is a great idea, rather than just implementing
the first idea that you come up with and just running with it until you're done.
I would say come up with a few different ideas, and maybe start implementing
a few of them, just a little bit at a time.
And when you feel like you've found something that feels truly clean, then commit.
Now, often, I don't know if this has happened to you in office hours,
we are working on one way to solve a problem, like say, A star, Katie,
tree, or whatever, and you're debugging, and you've spent four hours trying to
debug this compact little piece of code where you know there's something wrong,
but you're not sure quite what?
Yeah, quite what is wrong.
But sometimes really the best solution is take that file, like uncomment everything out,
and then just redo it from a fresh perspective, because what you're going to do is
it's approach it from a slightly different angle, and doing it from a clean and
informed perspective will get you better results.
That's kind of a different version of this, that rather than just trying as
hard as possible to get your first implementation work working, sometimes it's
best to set it aside.
And then in real systems, including Project 3, you should try and imagine how things
might need to change in the future, and I'll give some examples when we do our
exercise.
Okay, now again, I must note that this is extremely hard.
Me saying we'll just plan ahead, I think is a little dangerous, because no matter what you do,
there will always be mistakes.
I talked about the idea, for example, in Project 3 of having a design document where you have
to specify all the dependencies and classes and whatever else, but I find that next to
impossible to actually sit down and do something like that without programming, and especially
in 61B, I think it's tough.
So I guess what I would say, when you're doing Project 3, is avoid the temptation to
patch around the mistakes that you do make in your design.
Instead, I would actually take the time to step back and fix what's wrong.
So, I mean, just tiny example is S lists, we have that special case, and we could have
statements, but I think Sentinel nodes were a cool idea.
Okay.
Now, quick note, from an industry perspective, before we do our exercise, he talks about
how different companies have different cultures, and he describes that as a startup, when
Facebook was very small, which was not that long ago, Facebook embraced what he calls
tactical programming.
They have the slogan, move fast and break things, and basically you would get hired, and
it would be pretty normal for people to be building code and pushing it to the live site
within the first week on the job, things that code that people are actually
interacting with.
And so that's great, because when you're an engineer, it feels like you actually have
control.
You're just an employee, but I can actually change the way that messages are sent, or the
way that the feed is displayed, or what shows up in the feed.
And it also means the development is really fast in the short term, because you don't have
to go through more complex code review processes or whatever else.
Now, clearly, Facebook was incredibly successful, but its code base was noted as a mess.
So Osterhote, having the inside scoop, says that their code base was incomprehensible, unstable,
few comments or tests, and painful to work with, which made working there last month.
Now, eventually, they changed the company program in culture, and their motto became move
fast with stable infra, which certainly sounds less sexy, but I guess makes people's
jobs better.
Now, interesting note, and we'll talk about this in another one of our Friday lectures, is
the impact of how companies make decisions about what to work on.
And so Facebook, you could argue that their general attitude in life, this same kind of
theme has done great harm to the world, arguably.
And we'll talk in a future lecture, and I'll get some of your perspectives.
But obviously, they built this very powerful tool that has been released to the world, and arguably
has done damage.
Now, by contrast, there are other companies that have a more strategic culture, so he points
that Google and VMware.
And I will say that I've had this vision, but I have not yet done so of interning at Google,
or Facebook, or something, some summer, because it seems fun.
I have a friend at Google, who I was going to intern with summer ago, but then I didn't
want to commute to Mountain View from here, because it's too far, plus the baby.
Anyway, but he says that, because I wanted to know about their software practices, because
they teach this class, and I want to have more rural world stuff to bring you, because
it's been a while.
And so he says Google, a company known for its strategic approach to software, and VMware.
They place a heavy emphasis on high quality code and good design.
They build sophisticated products that solve complex problems with reliable software systems.
That's especially true if you're familiar with VMware, where they write software
that literally emulates operating systems inside of other operating systems.
Very technical and difficult work.
And so these companies, strong technical cultures, are well-known in Silicon Valley,
and few companies can compete with them to hire the top technical talent, whoever those people are.
Now, real world projects and companies, they succeed with either approach.
Obviously, Facebook is an enormously successful company, even though it's original technical
routes where maybe a little diceier.
Those two, though, then says, I think it'd be more fun to work somewhere with a nice
code base, so I guess if you trust them, you should work at Google in that Facebook,
but I don't know.
Anyway.
Yeah.
All right.
So, complexity.
Okay.
You know, let's see, do I want to just jump in?
Yeah.
I'm just going to say one more thing.
You know, this slide used to be earlier.
Oopsie.
Anyway.
Okay.
So, where the complexity come from?
It gives two examples.
Dependencies and obscurity.
Okay.
So, let's see if he has an example.
I'm getting rid of that slide.
We're going to come back to that one later.
Anyway, cal day.
Thanks for visiting.
Cool.
All right.
So, now what we're going to do is we are going to try and do an exercise to make obvious
code.
So, one of the most important ways to make your code obvious is to decompose it into separate
parts, which are often implemented as helper methods or subclasses or whatever else.
So, I'm going to try and exercise, which is inspired by bear maps.
And this is a very simplified version of something you'll do in that project, but you might find
it helpful to think about this.
So, the problem I'm giving you, arbitrary problem of the day, is that we have two, a two-dimensional
space that goes from zero to max x and zero to max y.
So, if max x is 100 and max y is 100, this is the space.
Okay.
It's small.
It's finite.
Now, let's say we break that space up into subspaces.
In this case, 16 of them.
Now, let's say I want to find all regions, sorry.
I want to find all of the regions that overlap a query rectangle.
This is very closely related to the rastering task on the assignment, though it's different
enough that I'm not spoiling anything, and it's easier in certain ways.
So, for example, if I have the rectangle 20, 90, so 20 over 90 up, and 40 comma 60, I end
up with, this is the answer to this problem would be AA, AB, BA, BB.
And I want to give the answer in level order.
So, AA, AB, AB.
So, solving this problem, this is fascinating to me.
Last semester, at the very end of 61B, after, I mean, 30 weeks or 28 weeks of an intense
Berkeley education, I was very surprised to see that a lot of people ran into a bit of
a brick wall, not with this problem, but something kind of similar.
And I think a lot of it really boiled down to jumping in and not thinking ahead.
So, I was just, I was surprised, I figured this list of problems going to be no problem
from my kids.
They're going to do good.
And a lot of people did fine, but it was just very interesting.
And I think my main advice is to think very carefully before jumping in.
So, what I'd like you to do is let's imagine we're writing this code above.
So, there's no rectangle, there's no AA, there's no BB.
All that stuff is just something you're going to have to produce, right?
So, all you have is a function that takes x1, y1, x2, y2.
And ultimately, you're going to have to return for this specific example, AA, AB, ABB.
The point is that the starter code is very simple.
So, let's suppose you're trying to solve this code above.
I'd like you to try and come up with an approach or two to solve this.
And what are some helpful methods you might imagine are useful, okay?
So, I'm going to leave this up here, and I will give you guys like, two,
what have we got to?
Let's do like two and a half minutes of pondering helper methods or approaches you might use.
Just let a very high level, and then I'll talk a little bit about what you might come up with, okay?
So, give it a shot, trying to forget how you solved this problem.
Now, one thing you'll note is that it's very hard to solve these problems,
so that a computer to try out a little bit of stuff, but give it a shot.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Okay, I would be curious to know if anybody has specific helper functions you want to suggest or approaches.
Either way, helper functions, things that might be useful.
Yeah.
Okay, got it.
So, we'll call this thing like x column, and you give it an x, and you could in principle
do this.
So, for example, if you have 23, so x column, I'll give you some input, output example.
So, we've got 23 would give you what?
All right, let's do like 15.
You give it 15, and what does it return?
There are 25 each, I guess, max x divided by 4 each.
0, like 33 would give you 1, 51 would give you 2, 76 would give you 4, something like that,
some examples.
Okay, I think that's a great example of a helper method that might be useful.
Out of bounds, that's interesting, so I don't know, private Boolean, I'll do in bounds.
What do you want?
This should really be a double by the way.
Double x, double y.
Okay, so that could be handy because you could throw exceptions.
So, it returns false if x, y is outside max x, max y.
Okay, I know that's not strictly speaking true.
We've got to say the other coordinate is zero, but I'm not going to do it.
Okay, so we could write that.
Okay, other helper methods that might be useful.
Yeah.
I mean, the vertices of the rectangle.
Uh-huh, 2090.
Uh-huh.
Oh, the other two.
Okay, that's interesting.
So, you could write, for example.
So, let's say you wanted to do that.
Now, what type would that return?
So, I want to return like upper right, where I give it the x1, double x,
or y1, double x2, double y2.
Okay?
So, what would it return, this upper right function?
Oh, so a list.
Okay, so a list of, let's say, doubles.
Okay, and this is a really interesting discussion.
Uh, so it returns a list of length two.
Is that right?
Oh, it's actually all.
Okay, I'm going to recommend that what you want really here is something like,
uh, I don't know, like, point 2D or something like that.
So, you can give a type that returns the upper right.
Though funny story, um, it turns out that,
I guess I'll import whatever this thing is.
Um, it turns out that this is not actually a useful method,
but it's unclear, right?
At least the approaches I might have.
Yeah.
Got it.
So, something like string.
Let's call it like a box string.
You give it double x1, double y1, double x2, double y2.
And this will tell you, in a specific location, what is that going to be?
So, you give it like this point, and it'll give you AA back.
Okay, last thing I want to ask is, what are some approaches?
If you have all these helper methods, what's something you could do to solve the problem?
What do you think?
Yeah.
Okay.
So, smallest x, which will always be, let's say that this is always the upper left.
So, let's say it's x1.
Yep.
Okay.
Which will be here.
So, I got the smallest and the largest x value.
Great.
Do the same thing for y.
So, you have a range of y values.
Yep.
Yeah.
So, you basically create a list, or you know the start x, the start y of ny, and you just iterate
over.
So, that's one approach.
What I think is the more natural approach.
The other approach that you may attempt, but is not a good idea.
One project to see is, let's just iterate over every possible box and say, is it valid?
I don't like that approach as much.
It's more complicated.
So, that approach is, let's look at AABACAD.
For each box, see if it intersects the rectangle.
I think it is more natural just to iterate only those rectangles you know are good.
I know that's a little vague.
But the big picture here is that these ideas, having these helper methods and mind you writing
tests to verify that they work, these are better building blocks, better types of abstractions
that will make your code more obvious.
And so, when you work on your raster, when you do a project to see, strive for obvious
code.
It'll make your life better.
It'll make the TAs happier in office hours.
All right.
Thank you everybody.
I hope you enjoyed this weird lecture.
There'll be two more weird lectures to come.
All right.
I think it was successful.